he finished describing uh different
kinds of objects of meditation that you
could use in the context of tying your
mind to the object chaining your mind to
the object right and that's how we got
on to the objects of meditation but it
was in the context of the second typical
problem of meditation which was the
elephant getting away okay the the
object
is I guess the po gets away but anyway
yeah the pole gets away all right the
mind is is the wild part the pole is the
and P away some all right
so so he was giving you different P you
could you could tie your mind to is the
air condition as cool as it
can make sure maybe sleepy all
right uh
having done that he goes on to discuss
which one's right for you here we
go I think we're at lock in
right
okay
yeah second okay here we go
uh in actual
practice you should pick the meditation
object which comes to you easily which
you know when you try to focus on it it
comes up in your mind
easily say my hard here's the important
part and until such time as that object
until such time as you have great
meditation on that
object uh
don't move to another object until such
time pick an object which is which fits
you and it might be Maham it might be
watching your
onl it might be an ous meditation it
might be thinking
about I like doing Thanksgiving
meditations just thinking about all the
people I have to think uh choose one
that seits you but my good partner how
you get good at it make call my don't
switch
another don't think you have to cover
all the four meditation objects that we
talked about last that was that were
described in by Lord Buddha in the
secret don't don't Sayo I didn't cover
all of them pick the one which sits you
and stick with
it uh
put your mind on one which fits your
heart it's your it's your
[Music]
own there
was this is a a scholar from anci
India single meditation object and make
it firm in your
mind super if you keep switching from
one meditation object to another you
need no more Super your mind will be
disturbed by negative thoughts okay your
mind will get Disturbed stick to one
another pick it carefully and then stick
to your tell you get go on whether it's
your LL or it's ous or whatever you
choose
when you are practicing meditation take
a single
make if you keep switching the object
you won't get sh won't be able to
[Music]
devel last
uh if you were ever a Boy Scout in
Arizona in 19
I we we had fire making contest and you
had to get a stick and a string and
another stick and you you have to you
know spin stick until it's m and then
from then on
it's so then they say when you're making
a fire by uh rubbing the stick against
the other stick right
uh if you keep switching sticks you
won't be able to get
fire
uh are not only that but when you are
trying to devel sh meditation
uh except for period this is especially
those of you who are going industry your
retreat except for period uh when you
sleep or prayers when you're eating or
sh means when you are going number one
and number
two uh except for those CS keep the keep
the keep the wood keep the fire stick to
the fire stick he says keep the fire
stick to the fire sck don't don't quit
keep keep going
okay except for the times when you have
to take a break keep keep
pushing because if you switching sticks
is one problem going for five minutes on
one stick and then stopping and then
going for five minutes two hours later
it's not going to
work may take you a year it may take you
six months but your CH child but don't
uh keep don't put large gaps in your
practice keep keep practice up daily and
don't if you're not in three Retreat
keep it up daily if you're in three
Retreat it's going be
more don't be like a person who gets
tired of one thing and moves on to
another and don't uh it's the same with
your yoga practice don't don't practice
hard to it's
G do a little bit everything rather than
heroic efforts on two days and then
nothing
[Music]
why didn't why when they talk about
the this what do they call problem
number three it's not called losing the
object it's called forting the
instructions and it doesn't mean that it
means drop it means losing the object
right and he says you know instruction
does come in here uh because if you're
taking for example uh if you're going to
meditate on a on a on a Buddha right
enlightened being
then you can go look at the statue for a
while and then you go sit down on your
seat and you close your eyes and you try
to think about it bring it in mind right
in time you will come say come
come listen listen to this
ready
are okay uh call
means to get used to something to get
become accustomed to something through a
constant constantly being around me uh c
means to meditate and one is the root
for the other you see meditation the
word of meditation into that means you
you are around the object of your
meditation so often that you get
accustomed to it and then it starts
coming to mind all the time
automatically like the image of your
heart L it just starts to come you're
sitting there having a you know rup and
this LV Parts up in your mind and that's
G and that's a result
of getting accustomed to your mind
is in the end he says in selecting the
object of your meditation depend on your
llam
advice you you have to have a heart
llama you have to have someone close to
you uh someone that you live near and
you can go to them and say what what AR
do you think I should be
meditating we'll we'll get to the
subject later but once you find your
hard mama you should stay near and then
you should be asking they should be
around and you should be able to ask
them your advice that's the whole point
so you should be able to say what what
are I should okay in the end you should
make a decision that
way you will know that you got your
meditation object in your
mind when you have a rough outline of it
in your mind that's enough for example
if you're trying to visualize your LL
their physical
appearance if you could just get their
silhouette down nicely you would have
already found the object see that's
that's you're already tied to the object
you don't have clity you don't have
intensity we don't have other qualities
that we'll talk about but in the
beginning you have reached the object if
you just get a silhouette that you can
hang on to
that's enough and that's a good way to
start with a Lama just as if they're
sitting behind a sheep with a light
behind them and you see their outline
that's that's how you start if you can
hold that outline you haven't lost the
[Music]
object but if you lose the silette and
you start taking a
about
lunch uh that's problem number two which
is called uh for getting the
instructions but which means losing the
object even a very a even a very
rudimentary object
[Music]
losing the antidote for problem number
two is antidote I'm sorry yeah the
antidote the problem number two is e
number because we used up the first four
already right I saw her thinking about
how close she was then I want her then I
work to get her and then I enjoy being
with her and I get good at it okay that
was all number one that was also problem
number one which was not getting like
doing am now we're have the problem too
which is you lose even the rough
out the antidote for that
is an number five what is anot number
five cha cha
means keeping the object in mind uh you
can say the word means remembering or
recollection but here it means like some
kind of awareness you know keeping
awareness of the object the object is
still aware of
the let an example
into that you know everybody had a
rosary around their wrist and you know
he's talking about how you would hold a
rosary you could hold it Loosely or you
could hold it firmly right uh if you can
apply the second sorry if you can apply
the fifth antidote when you have the
second problem it is similar to a firm
grasp on a Ros or a cup right like the
McDonald's what they say this is going
to burn your hand off if you spill it on
yourself like it's so weird they have to
tell people that right uh so it means
hold the cup a little bit with awaren so
don't do sloppy go slopp it on your
wrist and and and keep your mind keep
some part of your mind on holding it
firmly don't let it fall out your hand
on your
left and and then you'll be able able to
to sustain the grasp of the object
you'll be able to hold on to it for a
period in the yoga Sutra that's a
difference
[Music]
between
and LM number six which is just the
focus on the object and then LM number
seven which is the sustain focus on the
object
okay the word Gana was originally
pronounced in India
and when they got to China they called
it CH and Japes they heard zen zen
from okay all
right different people have different
abilities to sustain an awareness of the
right you know people who are spilling
things all the time you you do who knock
over cups all stuff like that and then
you know people who just never drop
anything and that's a that's a a sense
that's a capacity of awareness whether
you have a good capacity for maintaining
awareness of even a cup of coffee in him
or whether you have a poor capacity for
that will ultimately reflect in Your
Capacity to develop sham easily or not
if you have a
good minute by minute capacity to stay
aware of what's going on around you like
even in traffic from then you will find
it easier to develop
[Music]
sh what what exactly is that awareness
he's going to give you a more uh
detailed description of it from a book
called The
compendium there's two compendiums I
don't know which one they I believe it's
probably
theum
of but it could be could be a different
one what is it to have awareness toward
meditation it is a
mentality which performs the
function of enabling you not to lose or
forget an
object which you are growing in
familiarity awareness of coffee for
example the first time you had to hold a
cup of coffee in your life you were a
child somebody gave you a hot cup or
something and they said okay de hold it
a little tighter at the top and and
don't let it spill on you and then you
weren't so good at it you weren't
accustomed to it and later the awareness
because you became more used to having
hot things in your head and meditation
is the same so the awareness the
capacity to hold the cup firmly will
increase as you get more used to holding
cups of hot things like a
child so the idea
of getting good at maintaining a
meditation at maintaining a meditation
object is
defined as the as the familiarity you
build up with that object so let's say
you're
practicing uh your llama your root heart
llama is your meditation object right
the first day that you try to visualize
them it's going to be a little crude and
it won't come easily okay after a year I
mean you can spend a month on their eyes
you can spend just a month on the shape
of your LL eyes you know and and then
you can
uh because you're getting used to the
eyes then the object of meditation
becomes brighter and stronger so
meditation can be defined as an
increasing
familiarity with with an object because
you're meditating every day on it and it
becomes more and more commun I had a
really intense experience uh I was
staying in donala in the 70s and um I
lived next door to
Jah we wrote this wrote down this book
you know my llama's heart llama and uh
everybody said come on Mike let's go
see he was like 75 I said who am I to
bother such a high L you know like who
am I people were like banging out his
door all the time and I said leave the
die alone you know he's a high he's old
he's a high llama people are always
bother him just you know I never went
over there you and then I told my LL
about later and he yelled at me said
you're a fool you were a fool I never
met him he passed away I never got to I
Liv next door for months and I I made a
mistake I made
a anyway what somebody I know went over
there with a piece of blind paper and
they said
say could you draw a Buddha you know for
us and he went like
this and it was perfect because he was
drawing it from his meditation I had the
drawing but it's beautiful and he just
threw a freehand on the spot and he
handed because he was meditating all day
do that really beautiful
okay the kep
[Music]
so as you get more familiar with the
object it will rise in your mind sply
and he gives the
example of dinner when you're hungry
okay so it's not like you have to
struggle to bring up a vision of of your
favorite dinner when you're hungry you
get hungry and that triggers the vison
right got it uh your meditation should
become like that with the ease that you
remember your favorite food when you're
hungry you should remember your heart
Lama when you feel like meditating like
that like that the minute you sit down
it comes part
means un what do you call
unbidden
uny to
do like spontanously it just pops
up function of awareness is to prevent
your mind from wandering off another
other uh
so your your awareness should have this
qu therefore we can say that holding an
object before your mind's eye is what we
mean by uh
focusing holding the object before your
mind ey is what we mean by
you must learn to tie your mind to that
object in such a way that the mind
doesn't you have to try to struggle to
eliminate other objects around the and
and there's a thing in Buddhism about
uh the perception
of a person right
the perception of
t uh is is to eliminate everything else
in the room I I arrive at Petty by
eliminating every other object in the
room you see so in a way when you're
meditating you are bringing up the
object by eliminating all other objects
there's nothing else in the world just
think this in the middle of a meditation
thing there's nothing else in the world
but this this object even me it's not
even me it's just this never make it
[Music]
EAS this is very
interesting what's the third
problem like garbage
can
huh yeah uh all
either you get D either you get sleepy
or you or you or you start wandering
okay it's the same as listening to my
talk okay now your mind has to thread
between the two lines of garbage CS
right on either you'll get
sleepy and just kind of space or you'll
start thinking about or your mind will
leave in the room if your mind stays in
the room you might get sleep or your
mind might leave in okay why has that
occurred
why do you have
dullness and and why I'll give you a
clue okay why do you have dullness on
the object or wandering from the
object because you were on
the okay so
so makes an interesting note here you
know you get to the next problem because
you fixed the last thing got it you get
to the next problem because you fixed
the last thing you can't get dull on the
object if you don't reach the object
okay like if you never get to your
llama's form you can't get sleepy about
it or if you never get to your ll's form
in your mind you'll never think of lunch
and leave the form got
it what it means is the moment the
moment you've overcome your first big
obstacle and you're able to hold the
object immediately you're going to have
two other
problems you start facing or you'll
start taking yourself M you'll either
get dull the mind will get dark dull or
the mind will go somewhere why because
you
succeeded you got the object now now you
can have problems with the
[Music]
there are different forms of wellness
and agitation there are different I'm
going to call them wellness and
restlessness you can call them wellness
and agitation you can call them a lot of
things in okay there are also a lot of
ancient Sanskrit words and tietan words
to describe these problems he says if
you cannot distinguish between dullness
darkness and restlessness
then there's a problem that you will
never identify there's a big deal in
scripture about identifying your
enemy like you're in a battle in Tibet
people didn't have red uniforms and blue
uniforms you know it was just a bunch of
people Milling around on a big piece of
land killing each other and you didn't
know who was on what side right so I
mean you walk up to some guy and you
don't know if he's on your side or not
cuz there were no uniforms right so then
there's a a chance that you might not
recognize the real F dark shower means
the the real F if you can't distinguish
between dullness
Darkness
uh
restlessness and another one called W
okay you have to know the difference you
have to know the different ways in which
your mind will leave the object there
are like four or five different ways in
which you will screw up once you get the
off and you must be able to distinguish
between them
why each one takes a different antidot
okay you got to be able to say oh I'm
dull right now I got to use antidote
number six or whatever you know I'm I'm
n distracted I have to apply antidote
this other okay so if you cannot
identify the different problems your
mind is going to have
with the object you're not going to know
which tool to call out and fix it with
so you you have to be able to identify
the different ways in which your mind
will sneak away from
the here we
go so first he describes it's a word
called M mua means Darkness but it's
describing a state of mind okay it's
Darkness uh it's the third word up there
the okay m means Darkness here's what it
means your body and your mind feel heavy
need to go or some you feel like you're
about to follow that's Darkness that's a
really extreme form of d
like it's so bad you're going to fall
through I was in a very deep
meditation 36 years ago I remember I was
having a really deep meditation and it
suddenly started to fall apart you know
and I was like what's going on you know
what's happening and I examined my whole
mind I went from corner to corner place
to place where's the problem what's the
problem why am I losing the and then I I
said oh I'm
sleepy I didn't get enough sleep last
night you know so I just stopped when I
took him out okay
like sometimes you're just sleeping and
there there nothing you're going to be
able to do you know if if you didn't
have enough sleep the night before even
yoga is hard for me when I don't sleep
enough a that's a hard for me I don't
speak
about the problem with your meditation
may be simple as simple as getting
another hour sleep right and I asked k r
when I first got to H in
1904 and I said uh no I said R teach me
how not to sleep you know teach me how
not to need to sleep and he said forget
if you sleep as much as you need to if
it's s hours okay if it's 8 hours okay
if it's 9 hours okay you won't be able
to meditate well you don't sleep as much
as you personally need to okay some
people need six some people need nine
don't don't like judge yourself about it
you know that's who you are you don't
have to be
llam you never sleep that's what good
for him uh but you sleep as much as you
need because if you don't you won't be
able to meditate Muka is overwhelming
sense of heaviness bodily and mental and
you feel like you're about to fall me
it's extreme bonness
okay he says karmically speaking
M can be comically
neutral or it can be
comically non virtuous okay like
uh in traffic okay someone has to get in
your lane and you back off and you you
you wave to them and you let them goey
that's a virtue right all actions that
you do are one of three kind virtue is
to let them in front of you and you slow
down and you wave them up non virtue
is you speed up and try to make it so
they can't get into the leg okay but
what's between
there you kind of just let things happen
the way they're going to happen you
don't slow down you don't speak on
that's called lumatan lumatan means
karmically neutral you're not going to
get a bad coma from that and you're not
going to get a good coma from that it's
just like you're just
driving Darkness M darkness in in the
mind the feeling that you're about to
fall St at best it's comically
neutral at worst it's a bad de
right
however it will always lead to some
trouble it may not itself be karmically
bad you're not it may be to be sleepy in
a meditation is not a bad thing but it
will make you do it that got it it will
trigger some kind of
problem many of human beings problems
with each other are simply a lack of
enough sleep you know and you know that
you know the times when you start to get
anxiety about your life or it doesn't
seem like things you know everything's
dark uh it's no more uh what you call it
mysterious than you just didn't enough
sleep and get some take a nap and
everything will be suddenly
okay it's not that things
changed you just got a
sleep jingle now we get to maybe the
most
important part of the meditation
scripture okay this is the most
important part all
[Music]
right dness mental dness and meditation
can be divided into two different kinds
one is called called obvious dness you
can call Gross dness and one is called
sub
dness one is a very obvious kind of bate
of mind when you're trying to meditate
and one is more sneaky and the sneaky
one is the one we got a study because
you can mistake it for good medic here
we
go there are two forms of
dness uh obvious dness and then subtle
dness
[Music]
in the obvious form of dness you have
not lost
the object okay you're still on the
object right we're on to problem number
three number two is where you were
losing the object number three you're on
the object you are picturing your Llama
Or you are thinking about emptiness or
whatever
okay you're on the object you were
supposed to be
on and you have n n say
n
[Music]
nature I'm going to just Branch off here
and do those okay nature
means
uh nature
means fixation on the object fixation on
the object next means the part of
thing
fixation as opposed to sea sea means
brightness s means brightness I want to
call it
freshness the word means Clarity and
that word in English is dangerous why if
I say you have good fixation of the
object but you don't have Clarity what
comes to
mind you think the object is clear you
think oh the Llama has two eyes and not
one or you know like that and that's not
what Clarity means in this Cas Clarity
means how fresh is your mind how fresh
is your state of mind it does not refer
to the object it's not like is the
object blue or or red or bright or dark
or it doesn't Clarity in the study of
meditation means is your mind brigh eyed
and pushy T okay does your mind feel
fresh refreshed and excited and engaged
okay Clarity doesn't mean
what the object is not fuzzy it doesn't
mean that it means how sharp is the mind
and not how sharp is the
object so in the case of obvious
dullness which one do you have and which
one do you not
have fixation and
Clarity which one do you
have fixed you have fixation on the
object but you don't have Clarity
because your mind's not Frank you don't
feel fresh and bright and engaged okay
it doesn't mean the object's fuzzzy
right got that okay remember that a lot
of people misunderstood
that so grossness is where you do have
fixation but
no Clarity meaning the mind is is not PR
the mind is is tired and down right not
bright make and and later he's going to
say look this stuff you have to
experience I can talk to you about
freshness but until you meditate for a
few weeks or months you won know what
I'm talking about really you know you
you'll get there you'll be in a
meditation one day and you say oh my God
I'm fresh I got freshman yeah you be
saying I a got pre right now all right
[Music]
so what do you guys guess subtle dness
would
be in rock dness you have fixation but
you don't have
Clarity yeah in subas you do have
fixation and you do have clarity
your mind is fairly engaged okay but he
says your mind is what do you call it
Loose you have fixation and you have
Clarity but there's no they call
say you are going to have to spend a few
months trying to figure out what means
okay you have to experience it larm
means an intensity to the freshness
an intensity of the freshness you can
have somewhat some degree of freshness
is not enough you have got to have
intense
freshness okay it's the difference
between a good movie and an okay movie
sorry a great movie and an okay movie
how how are you how are you into it how
how deep are you into it it's the
difference between your favorite song
and your second favorite
song they play your favorite song I'm
going to play tomorrow can you see if
you got sound system
I I want to play a CD I'll bring my
computer so I have a piece of classical
music that just all it sends me and I
want to do yoga for that with you
tomorrow rather than telling you what
the hell is doing in the yoga
um but but the intensity of your
involvement in a piece of music that you
intensely love that's M okay subtle
dness means you do have a friend
freshness of Mind
somewhat and you do have
fixation but the there's no
intensity it's not an intense intense
Clarity of mind it's not an intense
brightness of the mind it's just an okay
brightness of the mind kind of a loose
brightness of
right if you want to know the greatest
Obstacle of all to meditation this is it
say
CH I think I could describe it as the
the marijuana state of mind okay it it's
like you know when you smoke marijuana
you feel happy right and you do feel as
though you're having some sort of
special engagement with objects like
objects are
more colorful or more intense right but
it's really sort of a dull State of Mind
it's not
like uh when you just did a good yoga
and you ate a good salad you know and
and you're like wow you know you're like
intense heal helpfully
intense it's different than if you're
like wow you
know it's a it's a bright intensity okay
it's a bright intensity your big
challenge in meditating and in January
we'll be doing it for real we're just
discussing the the manual for flying the
airport Mo we are not flying the airport
okay in January we fly and we stop
talking okay uh but when we get there
your big job is going to be can I catch
myself in some of
those
because everybody else in the world is
mistaken that for good
medication and it doesn't help you it
doesn't do anything you can't see
emptiness with
it feels
great you can sit there for 3 hours and
hold the object and you have some
brightness of Mone but there's no
intensity all right so that's that
becomes our big
enemy slightly defective great
meditation is the worst enemy of all all
right slightly defective what I great
meditation is worse than bad meditation
because bad meditation you know you have
to do something about it a slightly
defective great meditation you might
spend years there and you're doing good
all
[Music]
right what we mean when we say no
intensity is where you do have
fixation but you have sort of lost
the the the mind is sort of sloppy or
loose okay there's
no intensity there's just sort of a
looseness this is
inter and you got to think about I'll
say it and then let's all think about it
for minut he
says if your fixation gets too
good you flop into subtle
B if you overdo the
fixation it will send you into sub B I
gotta think me I got to think about
that if you overdo the holding to the
object and you it's like holding a
football too tightly and then it spurts
out of your hand you see or holding a
cup too tightly and then it just pushes
up
see over doing the over doing the
fixation will flop you into
subtle you have to think about that
probably you have to check it well
that'll be on our list okay for January
let's try to see what it's like
to to lose the intensity because we were
holding too hard we were trying to hold
on too hard think about it
singing when we say that you have
intensity to the freshness of your mind
what it means is you have a
pleasant a pleasant degree of
concentration a pleasant degree of
concentrating on the
object that's that's intensity of
refreshment is a refreshing
quality of con of what's a better word
for
contion what you say when somebody's
driving and they you know say wait wait
you should
be I think concentrate maybe just STV
with concent concentrate on your driving
someone
like
and g
means pay attention pay attention good
pay attention concentrate if the G is
concentrate
so intensity of the freshness is a kind
of pleasant
cont intensity of refreshness is a
refreshing
[Music]
con I want to tell you he says I want to
give you an example of having freshness
and having fixation
but not having intensity of effect all
right I want to give you an example for
that P Zim suppose you are holding your
Rosary or monks have a p you know
por Fus a little wooden bow that she go
to the morning prayer with
why they will serve hot tea if you can
if you show up otherwise you don't get
up that's why everyone comes Med all
[Music]
right when you are holding
your
or you can be holding it firmly a cup
right or you can be holding it Loosely
in which case you might spill the teeth
all
right so the difference between
intensity with your freshness or lack of
intensity with your freshness is similar
to holding a bowl in your hand a bowl of
hot tea and holding it in a
responsibly semi firm way or holding it
in a careless way in which it might
still un hurt you all right that's the
difference between intensity and no
intensity it's a quality of the degree
of steadiness in the homework
okay it's hard right it's hard to
describe the mental things in words
R I like his next example very very much
I really like his next
example and this is the beauty of this
book okay the difference between this
book and some c book from the 15th
century is that he he's got this war he
got this gentlement he's got this I
don't
know it's just friendly somehow it feels
warm
he says uh you know think about your
your lung think about your heart L
okay
H in general you have faith in them
right you do have faith in your
heart but should prce
mea but you know most of the day it's
not like
overwhelming like you start to cry or
something like that like you have faith
in your llama and you think about them
you know
in a devoted
[Music]
way but every once in a while you're
thinking about your heart llama and you
suddenly break into te you know it's
like too much you know it just
overwhelms it you're just like oh my God
you know I have this person in my life
you know and then you just you just
break down okay that's intensity of the
devotion as opposed to
devotion so freshness with intensity is
similar it just the fres shoots up to
new LEL B Jima B Jima means it shoots up
to new level just intense intense
engagement of the mind like in your
favorite piece of music or in your
favorite movie or the best page of your
favorite book and you know your mom's
calling you and you don't hear it right
like or your favorite T voice to the
Bottom of the Sea you know they're about
to kill the giant squ you know like and
then your Mom is calling you for
spaghetti dinner and and you don't even
hear her you see that's intensity
all there's a word for that in
[Music]
say anyway
so you can
say that the the intensity with which
you are embracing your heart Lama in
those special moments when you break out
C is is different from the intensity
other one right that's that's a
difference of of uh
say holding
the there must be way
it means to be holding on to the object
perly talk like you
call ading in a strong
super as opposed to
El really it's it's a difference of the
tightness of the bond somebody said Bond
there a difference in the tightness of
the
B that's a good maybe that's a good way
to
say so these are good examples to
describe what we call
[Music]
in my said who's saying that my llama
said this is
Che my llama
said these are things which you can only
really know
through personal practice I he says
SE these are not things you can describe
perfectly in words right I can talk to
you about intensity all day but you're
like you know go home and mention it to
somebody what did you what did they say
at the Elric T like they talking about
intensity of
freshman you're like what are you
talking about and then you're like I'm
not my shirts you know and uh it's
something you have to learn by in
January or hopefully before that you
know we will explore these things you
know let's go looking for some of Bas in
J in Prescott he's probably there
fromwhere behind a
tree uh and we have to go look for him
like that
[Music]
say Clarity or
clearness you we are not referring to
the office this is what I said now he's
gonna say
understand that when we speak of clarity
we are not speaking about how clear the
object looks we are speaking
about the freshness of the Mind the
brightness of the Mind
the when you don't have freshness of the
mind it almost feel feels as like a
shadow passing over
your it feels like you know like if a
big truck drives by you and the shadow
envelops you envelops you evul you for a
moment and then leaves he says that's
how losing your mental freshness feels
like it feels like a shadow has passed
through
your now he gets to a very crucial point
in subtle dness do you have
fixation do you have
Clarity so there's a very grave danger
that you will mistake that for good
medical see he's saying
that and and frankly you meet people in
some traditions or even in this
tradition who are just Spacey all the
time they because they meditate in so
Wellness Allah lot they are they are
holding the object well they are not
moving and they are not their nose
they're not doing texts and they're not
grabbing Cups of Tea they are sitting in
cross-legged position with a straight
back and they haven't moved in half an
hour or 45 minutes but the mind is stuck
in subtle BS they are spacing out they
are just zoning out okay they are not in
a Zone they are zoning out all
right and and it's very hard distinction
right it's a very subtle distinction and
and and your life depends on making the
distinction right whether or not you
will see the high objects that will save
your life and save the lives of those
you love depends on can you make this
distinction can you divide these two
things by the way a person who doesn't
meditate regularly doesn't have this
problem all right they'll never have
fixation anyway and they certainly don't
have Clarity uh they're just thinking
about one all right
okay they need ction to distinguish
these two things
is you can sit in D subtle dness and
meditation you can even get to a point
where your breath stop right generally
speaking when you reach the spontaneous
retention of the breath which is in yoga
in yoga is called
what when you reach the spontaneous
suspension of your breath it's an
excellent sign it's a really really good
sign it means you are close to seeing
everything if you
suddenly become aware that you haven't
breathe for 5 minutes you are close to
seeing everything so generally speaking
it's a good thing but it can also happen
with so it's St
and you can sit there for a whole day
and not move and being in so dous it's a
dous thing if you don't learn anything
else about meditation in these 10 days
learn
that spacing out is not is
not so it so some meditation Masters in
the days of your into that
okay they
had it
means I gotta get it's
[Music]
poetic great meditation is great
release that's not so good great
meditation is great surender something
like that they had a saying like
that and and they said
um just release your hold on the
upate they
interpreted the famous saying great
meditation is great releas to mean just
Zone up don't think about anything in in
in America they said don't think about
anything whatever thought com in the
mind simply Let It Go the Mind watch it
watch it come don't hold on to it don't
connect to it don't don't make it what
you call that don't don't identify with
it just let it go you know this is L
this is a Mis
interpretation of the expression great
meditation is great letting go how that
great meditation is great there was such
a saying by the bud great meditation
great it doesn't mean that it doesn't
mean mean to just sit there and not try
to think about anything try to think
about matter all right which the better
you get at the more you are thinking
about
something it's a contradiction it's it
all right there we
go now now very interesting and very
important Point what will happen to
you if you fail to identify subtle
dullness in your
what will happen if you keep that up
year after year what do you
think it's the pop thing for me it's the
PO thing
you you know okay he doesn't say po
thing we didn't have
PO he says D soon make something
WR there are certain deep kinds of
meditation which are so deep that after
if you practice them your whole life and
you
die in that state or with in under the
influence of those stes you will go the
other
realm and they are they are very cool
Realms you know you spend many thousands
of years in some kind
of uh space
out okay in in our tradition it's
considered undesirable because it's
temporary and you fall after that you
fall out
it's like you can reach a place if you
meditate wrong for your whole life if
you do Fair good meditation your whole
life and you die suddenly your mind
doesn't come back to a PR like this your
mind goes to some higher temporary blant
Breath
Right he but he
says you can't even get to that
withness will even scre you up from
doing that which is a non goal okay you
can't even get non go if you have subtle
dos that's what he's saying say dear
young J if you keep up this subtle thing
you will become some kind of
space space is J okay J space
no J means in my when I was young they
call the absentminded professor Sy you
know you just go around and you're like
oh where did I put my iPhone you know
and oh I have my keing there somewhere
you know and you know what do you call
it they're always thinking about
mathematics or something and they you
know they they're always leaving stuff
somewhere dropping stuff like that's
called
Ding abent minded Professor if you want
to be an abent minded Professor do
subance meditation frequently okay sh go
this is something more serious you will
lose capacity
for for intellectual thinking you will
be unable to have a serious discussion
with anything with anybody about
anything politics or or science or
morality or or you know philosophical
questions you will lose the sharpness of
Mind required to you will lose
intellectual
rigor you you just become sort of you
can't Gras uh find points
but you just spaced out hour after
hour these are the kic results of
spacing out
frequently V something fun it
says what's a
d
what's what's the s
of s
just okay what's s
s is what you been going to do for three
years day pleas
you what
[Music]
is yeah the word s means to reach to
reach somebody
who yeah you good means a a ritual that
you engage in maybe six times a day or
four times a day in order to reach a
Divine good gr top means a way of
reaching and as an noted it can mean two
different kinds of reaching what are
they one is to meet them okay I mean you
get to meet at in they come to your
cabin even though the doors aren't
completely finished
yet they still come cuz they they're
like they can come to the and uh they
you you make contact that's one meaning
of son what's the other one you become
them you turn into them and then you
hang out with
them he says subtle is a what's that
mean selfness is a
s
d what's a dundo dundo is an animal
animal re an animal you want to be
reborn as a as a turtle or
something and and this is not talking
about dolphins who save humans and stuff
like that this is talking about no this
is talking about like really slow
Turtles something like that like their
mind state is is dull and Americans
don't like to hear that they like to
think the animals are having a good time
even though they're killing each other
muchly all day um you know but they are
dull you can't sit and talk to a turtle
and explain to them the difference
between subtle bonness you know if you
want to take a rebirth as a creature
whose mind is extraordinarily
dull which is the standard explanation
of an animal it's not always the case
okay there can be animals who are Divine
beings who are who are showing
themselves as an animal to teach you
something but there are also animals who
are good
do and they die because they're dull
cows get slaughtered because they're
dull and they sit there and eat the
grass and they never figure out if
they're going to get killed they can't
talk to each other and warn each other
it's just the nature of their mind if
you want to be like that then keep up
subtle dness okay it it becomes a s for
that all right got
it okay LIF up to you BL the C it's
almost as if you were purposely doing a
sign of to take a rebirth out the C
more okay he finished the first half of
problem number
three we got to talk about the other
line of garbage P okay we finished now
we're on to call agitation Restless
thinking about lunch as opposed to
falling
asleep we had a big discussion me and
love Victory IND can you have a p ofo
Ando at the same time you know the V of
the body are collections of K which
perform functions so when you have to
digest food you know the the S V comes
all the product collects near your
stomach and it helps you chew up the
grind up the food right uh a of helps
you eliminate food and Menses and other
things SE and then udana helps you speak
or eject things through your mouth so we
having this debate about could you have
two V operating at the same time and we
went to a restaurant to to talk about it
in v n and we must have eaten something
really
done and we both in a ditch across the
street had the experience that you can
have both of
those at the same
[Music]
time why did I mention
it oh yeah did you have D and the same I
mean we could try that would be like a
go you know could you fall asleep and
think of Ls at the same time it's
possible but we can work on
it I think this might not be plugged in
yeah so now we're on
to restlessness thinking about lunch as
opposed to falling asleep all right now
we're on tonight's
class what time suppos to
start like 1: behind
us okay that's all right
[Music]
I yeah we just finished the
right a little
okay here we go on class and we will
stop
[Music]
on
restlessness the same book
says what does it mean for the mind to
be rest
it is an unsettledness of the
mind but it's specific where the mind is
attracted to something that is the mind
is sorry the mind is distracted to
something that finds attracted okay the
mind is distracted to something that
finds attractive like
lunch or the last boy you met or the car
that you want or the that you are right
those are
all there's a quality of the object what
is it it's
attractive so restlessness is the
opposite of of dness is Define as the
Mind distracted to something it find
pleas and there and then the Mind
becomes
unsettled and it functions to and block
the information sh you cannot learn to
reach a deep state of meditation if you
have this mind did I give you a break
tonight
[Music]
go probably go to non break
okay it is it is the mind
uhing
things he wants to give an example for
an attractive object he's going to give
an example of the object that you might
have trouble with if you happen to
you they didn't have
t uh they had jar jar is uhar andar I
saw duar I was in G in 1973 something so
there were still knew how to do Bard
pretty well and they people dress up
with these huge masks and and they they
wear these big costumes and then they
come out and they
go and everyone's
like you know um uh and you can't
understand a single word I I asked
everybody what's she singing what's she
saying I said nobody
knows and it's supposed to be this story
of some old king or something and it's
break it's like this Swan life done in
an opera and you have no say screaming
in Italian and you don't know what it's
about you know anyway that's a good that
was the
opin uh let's say he says you go to a
bill cart during the day then you get
home and then they evening you're
sitting having dinner and suddenly the
main actor or main actress comes to mind
you know that handsome boy or that
beautiful girl com to mind that's a
desirable mental inage okay he's giving
example what's his
[Music]
name kind of
nauy uh not George uh what's his
name it's Brad Pit yeah okay Brad Pit
popping into your mind is is a desirable
object okay I mean if you're into
[Music]
okay because you just went to see his
movie and or Angela Billy pops up in
your mind you went to see uh
salt and uh and you came home and then
she popped up in your M that's that's
what
that's
that's this is interesting it says we
draw a distinction between distraction
and restlessness we draw a distinction
between distraction and
restlessness and it's not evident in the
words in English and it's not evident in
the words in
you you have a person at work who is
constantly picking on you your
supervisor right if they keep popping up
in your mind brain meditation is that
the restlessness that we have just
become why we are not in
other right so that doesn't classify as
restlessness in the study of medication
it is not the second line of garbage
cans to be distracted by thoughts about
your mean boss and how he was mean to
you today or your ex-wife or whatever
all right it's
not that's it's bad but it's
not know okay here's another
example what if you're trying to
develop single pointed concentration
towards the holy form of your heart
teacher and suddenly you start thinking
about a project to raise money for the
retreat C know is that is that
restlessness they would say
no they would say it's a virtuous object
but it's not an desire object right so
there's some kind of negative
connotation desire has sort of a
negative connotation like food or sex or
TV or something like that but but to be
distracted to a virtuous object is not
classified as a desire object so if you
start thinking about fundraising
projects and you're supposed to be
concentrating on your LL
form is that
shat it's a it's a it's a you call
obacle to sh even a virtuous thought
which doesn't apply to your chosen
meditation object is a is a serious
obstacle and and you have failed in your
meditation even to have uh kind thoughts
charitable thoughts about something
other than the form of your holy llama
if you have chosen the holy form of your
Lama as a meditation object is to fail
in your meditation meditation means
you're focusing on the object that you
chose and other objects are all even if
they're virt right it with that so that
doesn't qualify as restlessness even to
think about fundraising projects by the
way when you're in your retreat oh
man we have 10,000 projects within six
weeks avoid it okay you can do them when
you get off you can think about it when
you get off keep your mind on your
object you don't make Grand plans about
you know I'm going to rebuild the world
CER
and put a big booger face on the to you
know you you know I swear in a threee
tree you get like thousands of little PL
you can write them down and burn
them
okay so an interloc wow that word has
come up
somebody comes and asks a question okay
somebody comes up and ask question in
the text right it says now listen if I
think of a fundraising project in the
middle of trying to develop sh on my
holy Lama's beautiful fantastic incable
form why is that an obstacle to sh or
not what do you think it is cu you're
not single
pointed
Okay so why not classify it as
restlessness isn't it being Restless to
think about a virtuous project when
you're supposed to be thinking about
something else isn't that Restless yes
or no it is restless I mean your mind is
restless it's going off to something
else so this guy asks a person a
perfectly reasonable question he says
why do you reserve distraction
towards desire desire objects as an
obstacle to Sham in problem number
three but you don't list thinking of
other stuff like your angry boss or your
fundraising progress why don't you list
those as problem number two why do you
only classify as problem number three
distraction towards pleasure pleasure
objects somebody asked the question
because they are equally obstacles to
your
sh he says make
the fact is that being distracted to
virtuous projects is
less and being even being distracted to
people you're angry at is is infinitely
pure than distractions about what do you
want to do and what do you want to get
all right what do you want to do and
what do you want to get distractions are
99% of all
this in a normal person all right unless
you just got the bo
all
[Music]
right 99% of your distractions are what
what you want to do or what do you want
to get okay new
and even if you do have a thought about
your boss it normally won't last very
long and especially if you have a
thought about fundraising because
someone else's cabin that's not going to
last very
long but if you start thinking about all
the stuff you want for you now back you
can sustain all right given that fact we
classify distraction to a desire object
as being the obstacle to shamata at this
point in problem number three because
they're so prevalent and they're so
sustained it's not that the other ones
are not
obstal it's that this one is 99% of your
problem thinking about
lunch is more frequent than thinking
about your BS by far and more sustain
especially if you don't get much like
the RTV breaks down right Rob I mean
whatever thanks for
Happ generally speaking when we try to
meditate the thing that disturbs our
mind is normally stuff we want to for
our
also it's a lot easier to get thought
about something you want than it is to
think about someone you don't like it's
just easier it's more
[Music]
what
therefore in the practice of developing
deep meditation when your mind goes to
an object which is unpleasant to you we
classify it as
distraction right when you uh are
thinking about uh virtuous activities
such as fundraising projects or doing
frustrations like
that this is also a kind of distraction
but not
restlessness she may go make CSU make
part they they not got good
s but they also block your sh and you
have to you have to try to fight them
have try to fight them I think the
lesson we can learn from that last
discussion is that and this is very very
important
okay most of the people in this room I I
believe are very good people I believe
that most of the people in this room are
really working hard to help other people
uh but to start thinking about that when
you're supposed to be developing single
pointed meditation on a particular
object is a bad be it's a mistake okay
so don't especially in a threeyear
retreat don't don't fool yourself okay
your job is to or whatever you choose
your job is done okay don't start
thinking about the World Trade Center
and putting a a Buddha place on the top
of the center when you're supposed to be
getting by to come to your cabin
all right because that becomes a an
obstacle then the world trainer Center
becomes an obstacle goodness becomes an
opticle got
it choose your meditation object
carefully and then stick to it and
eliminate all other F in in especially
in a retreat because you're going to be
thinking about 10,000 projects you can
do when you get out and you'll waste the
whole time thinking about what the
biggest waste of time in a threee
retreat is thinking about what you're
going to do after the Comm
but you can think about after the the
all right all
[Music]
right uh I'll keep you for about another
minutes what I'm trying to do is finish
by tomorrow so people just come for the
weekend and get the whole thing on
meditation we go to
he begins to make a distinction between
obvious restlessness and subtle
restlessness in the same way that he
made a distinction
between thas
andas obvious thas and
what was obvious
doar about to fall
asleep what was
subtle you have fixation you have some
clarity you don't have
them L can refer to the temper on a
knife that's another good example the
word Nar refers to temper on a knife I
don't know how they temper feel they
they raise the heat on it and then cool
it suddenly or something I don't know
you put a temper on a spel tempered
blade will hold its sharpness much
longer than a blade which hasn't been
tempered lar can also mean temper on a
blade something that makes it more
intense this cutting power becomes more
intense It's ability to hold sharpness
BEC more
[Music]
intense if you lose the object
completely right for example
if you are trying to meditate on your
llama's Divine fantastic beautiful
unable us and then
suddenly he calls it jika jik means
meltdown you have a mental meltdown all
right
and dra you lose the object completely
okay
that's close
okay you melt down on the object and you
go to something that's gr do you have
fation
[Music]
okay here's subtle what restlessness all
right very subtle very beautiful he says
imagine a stream in the winter the K
River Lea in the winter okay the top
freezes over right and then under the
top the water is Flowing you see so
picture that a river the top 4 in is
frozen but there's still this torent
moving under the ice okay he says uh in
subtle restlessness we haven't lost the
object right we have not lost the object
but a certain corner of your mind is
running below your Consciousness below
your manifest thoughts there's a sub
current what do you call
undercurrent of of thinking about
something you like and it's very
beautiful word inet those of you who are
studying for the say Charla K Charla K
the important word here is k h a d k k
means just about to burst
out there's there's thoughts about lunch
are running just under your conscious
mind and it'll just take a little crack
in the ice and you'll hey what's the
lunch you know are they making a
delivery this afternoon isn't it Monday
is I talk two
then the the lunch thoughts running
under the eyes broke up broke out so
several restlessness is
what those desired thoughts are they're
not stopped that we haven't come to the
conscious mind yet we haven't thought
about lunch yet but it's ready under the
mind right under the consciousness of my
new car my new job my new boyfriend it's
there all those thoughts are running in
the subconscious right that's subtle
restlessness and it will break out it
will crack the ice will crack and then
it will move into gross restlessness and
you'll start thinking about your
B then you've lost the object and your
the rest of this has gone from SLE to OB
all right good next
income very interesting point here I got
seven more minutes of your
life if you check the meditation chart
which you should do for fun okay go hope
tonight see how many of the things on
there you know so far right those of you
who got the chart uh you know in your
free
time
uh go over the chart and see how much of
it you know already the St you're going
to get tomorrow
hopefully um the
antidote for this problem of vness and
restlessness is called
[Music]
watchfulness
watchfulness in they call
say means you reserve a corner of your
mind to watch the rest of your mind
while you're meditating
you you said in in tiet it's called SOA
or jar
SOA SOA jar means a
spy okay it means a spy you you have an
undercover guard in the corner of your
mind and you say look you don't
participate in the meditation okay you
watch The
Meditation you you say to a corner of
your mind hey you you watch me meditate
if you see me start thinking about lunch
ring a bell ding ding ding ding all
right got it that's
sh the correction of problem
number tree is is watch for he's
watching you meditate corner of your
mind that's watching you meditate and
the minute you you start getting sleepy
who
goes or or the minute you start thinking
about lunch is or about your fundraising
projects in the middle of your three
Retreat he's
like now question for you does that fix
the
problem no okay
so from this is not the actual antidote
to number three but traditionally it's
called the
antidote all it does is what it just
alerts you to a problem it doesn't fix
the problem it alerts you to a problem
but it doesn't fix the problem
but traditionally it's considered the
antidote which must mean that the
antidote comes next all right but if you
don't have an alarm go off you will
never apply the OT because you won't
know you have a problem because if your
mind is 100% in the meditation and you
don't have part of your mind watching
your mind you'll never catch yourself
you'll just keep doing that subtle dness
thing that marijuana meditation thing
you've got to have part of your mind
that can ring the one and that's called
sh that's the antidot to problem number
three additionally obviously we're going
have have
another coming soon right I still got
four minutes now I'm going to need
it
however the watchful State of Mind The
Watcher what you call it what do you
guys want to call
it
monitor okay you follow that all right
uh he says for
example it's as if you had set a lookout
on a hill to watch the movement of the
enemy troops got it okay
CH in order to detect whether you have
fallen into bonness or restlessness you
have to apply the sixth of the which is
just watchfulness
watchful
mental Lookout how about Lookout okay a
mental Lookout in the back of your
head this is a very very interesting and
subtle Point all right
if you overdo the lookout thing what
will
happen it will break your
fixation right you overdo the lookout
thing that will break your meditation
that will break your fixation point we
can be Brie and bushy pil Lookout but
that's going to ruin your fixation all
right don't overdo the lookout thing
check in from time to time am might
thinking about lunch
yet all right
on the other hand if you underdo the
lookout thing
sing you can have a problem developing
in the meditation and you won't be
aware a problem will come up the
meditation will start to go off
meditation will start to degenerate and
you will know if you underdo the lookout
thing if you overdo the lookout thing
illus your fixation you want to do the
lookout thing you have a problem during
the meditation and you don't even know
you're having a
problem you have to Le a
mle it's like uh realizing that someone
has broken into your truck and stolen
your electric
piano
okay like you got to know that it's
happening you got to know when it has
happened then you can do something
one minute
[Music]
is
teachings what is m in this sense
it's the it's where the object of
meditation is your own
mind how would look out figuring
that well somehow it would be on like
having an automatic Lookout you see if
you were engaged in your mind as your
object of meditation it would be by
Nature already a look all right so in
when you're doing M movement meditation
the lookout part is almost all the
matter that's what he's trying to say
you doation go uh set a part of your
mind to the job of watching the rest of
your mind
run sh try to get your spy your Lookout
should be
positioned ahead of time cup cups
chinger and from time to time he should
check in on your M right it's not doing
it all the time because then you would
lose your extension he's doing it he
hasn't gone to sleep completely and and
and stop looking out or else you would
just ruin your meditation you would get
into a problem and not know you were in
a problem right
[Music]
okay that's the one more L okay
CH send make
meditation check
in Fairly frequently on the condition of
your body and your mind are you sitting
up straight still are you still not
moving okay are you are you still
holding the physical positive meditation
well and how's your mind doing is your
mind watered yet has your mind gotten D
yet
this is what it means to put a
lookout this is what it means to put a
lookout someone who checks from time to
time on the conditioning
body CH food B it was spoken all
right we didn't finish tonight's class
so do as much homework as we can and I I
didn't want to get behind but I also
don't want to burn you out there was a
long
day so uh
pause there